Guide to the Consumer Reports. Consumers Union Foundation records, 1938-1991 RL.11856
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports. Consumers Union Foundation records
1938-1991
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Consumer Reports (Firm)
RL.11856
10.0 Linear Feet
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Consumers Union Foundation was established in 1971 as a nonprofit focused on fundraising and promotion of consumer-based research projects. The Consumers Union Foundation (CUF) records include correspondence, direct mail examples, financial statements and reports, grants and internships, meeting minutes, project notes and reports, research reports and other printed materials. The collection also includes materials relating to an oral history project on people active in the consumer movement, and notes and drafts for a history of the Consumers Union. Organizations represented include the Consumer Interests Foundation (precursor to the CUF), the Center for the Study of Consumer Movements research center, and the Consumer Policy Institute (and its predecessor the Institute for Consumer Policy Research), a subsidiary of Consumers Union. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series: General and Administrative Files; Consumer Interests Foundaton; Center for the Study of Consumer Movements; Consumer Policy Institute
Biographical / Historical
Consumer Reports is a product testing and consumer advocacy nonprofit organization based in Yonkers, N.Y., founded in 1936. Consumers Union Foundation was established in 1971 as a nonprofit focused on fundraising and promotion of consumer-based research projects. The Consumer Interests Foundation was established in 1971 to promote research into consumer interests (such as consumer education, the environment, healthcare, housing, poverty) not related to product testing. It was renamed as Consumers Union Foundation in 1975. A research center, the Center for the Study of Consumer Movements was established in 1972 with a NEH grant and other funding. In 1979 Consumers Union created a subsidiary, the Institute for Consumer Policy Research, to promote research and advocacy on policy-based consumer interests. It was renamed the Consumer Policy Institute in 1990.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Consumer Reports. Consumers Union Foundation records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2019.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Consumer Reports Archives records
Consumer Reports. Advocacy records
Consumer Reports. Washington Office records
Consumer Reports. Colston E. Warne papers
Consumer Reports. Eileen Nic papers
Collection Overview
The Consumers Union Foundation (CUF) records include correspondence, direct mail examples, financial statements and reports, grants and internships, meeting minutes, project notes and reports, research reports and other printed materials. The collection also includes materials relating to an oral history project on people active in the consumer movement, and notes and drafts for a history of the Consumers Union. Organizations represented include the Consumer Interests Foundation (precursor to the CUF), the Center for the Study of Consumer Movements research center, and the Consumer Policy Institute (and its predecessor the Institute for Consumer Policy Research), a subsidiary of Consumers Union.
Consumer education; Consumer advocacy; consumer protection; Consumer Interests Foundation; Consumers Union Foundation; Consumers Union Foundation. Center for the Study of the Consumer Movement; Institute for Consumer Policy Research; Consumer Policy Institute
- General and Administrative Files, 1973-1985; 1
  - Advance Notice newsletter, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Annual Meeting, 1978-1979; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Balance sheets, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Board of Trustees, 1973-1981; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Bylaws, Certificate of Incorporation, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Consumer Education Resource Network (CERN), 1982 (Box 1)
  - Constribution acknowledgements, 1982-1985 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, memos, 1975-1982; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, memos, 1983-1984 (Box 2)
  - Council of Better Business Bureaus, 1983-1985 (Box 2)
  - Direct mailings, approximately 1983 (Box 2)
  - Financial statements, 1978-1984; 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Foundation funding, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Management, 1980-1984; 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Meetings, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
  - Meetings, 1979-1981; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Minutes, 1976-1981 (Box 3)
  - Persia Campbell: Portrait of a Consumer Activist, 1980-1981; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Promotional packets, 1981-1985 (Box 3)
  - Tax information, grants, 1982 (Box 3)
- Consumer Interests Foundation, 1971-1981; 2
  - Automobile advertising substantiation, 1972-1973; 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Automobile advertising substantiation, 1972-1974; 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Automobile advertising substantiation, 1973 (Box 21)
  - Automobile emissions, 1972-1973; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Board of Directors, 1971-1973; 5 folders (Box 4)
  - Board of Trustees, 1972-1973; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Bylaws, Certificate of Incorporation, 1971-1973; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Certificate of Incorporation, 1971-1972 (Box 21)
  - Correspondence--Edward Vitello, 1971 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence, memos, 1971-1975; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Document binder, 1972; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Donations, 1972-1973 (Box 5)
  - Environment--Do Citizen Suits Overburden Our Courts?, 1973; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Environment--Do Citizen Suits Overburden Our Courts?, 1973 (Box 21)
  - Executive Committee, 1972-1973; 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Financial reports, 1973; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Management letter, 1974 (Box 6)
  - Minutes, 1971-1972; 3 folders (Box 6)
  - Minutes, 1972-1981; 3 folders (Box 7)
  - Reports, 1972 (Box 7)
- Center for the Study of Consumer Movements (CSCM), 1938-1988; 3
  - General and Administrative Files, 1952-1988; 1
    - A Guide to Documents of the Consumer Movement, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Accessions: Books and other materials, 1973-1977 (Box 7)
    - Acquisitions: Films, publications, theses, tapes, 1973-1975 (Box 7)
    - Advisory Committee, 1975-1979; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Alan Goodman, 1972-1974 (Box 7)
    - Alan Goodman, 1972-1974 (Box 21)
    - Annual and Interim Reports, 1974-1979 (Box 8)
    - Brochures, newsletters, 1979 (Box 8)
    - Consultants--Archival work, 1973-1974 (Box 8)
    - Consultants--Ronald Grele, 1973 (Box 21)
    - Consumer Library, 1978-1980 (Box 7)
    - Consumers Union history--Source materials (Eirlys Roberts), 1966 (Box 21)
    - Correspondence, 1973-1976; 5 folders (Box 8)
    - Correspondence, 1977-1981; 5 folders (Box 9)
    - Correspondence--Colston Warne, 1970-1974 (Box 9)
    - Correspondence--Researchers, teachers, etc., 1973-1975 (Box 9)
    - Documentary: Western Consumers Union 1938-1940, 1974 (Box 9)
    - Documents for History List, 1936-1978 (Box 9)
    - Drafts: Evolution of Consumers Union Board structure, 1973-1975 (Box 9)
    - Film review: Visit to Consumers Union (1969)--Staff comments, 1974 (Box 9)
    - Films--Storage, 1977 (Box 10)
    - Foundation proposal--American Revolution Bicentennial Administration, 1975 (Box 10)
    - Jean Halloran--Statement before U.S. House Subcommittee, export of unapproved drugs, 1984 (Box 10)
    - John Dunne testimony before U.S. Senate Subcommittee on labor and human resources, 1984 (Box 21)
    - Legal agreements, 1972-1981; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - NEH grant, 1974-1980; 4 folders (Box 10)
    - Norman Katz, 1974-1975 (Box 10)
    - Oral history project, 1974-1988 (Box 10)
    - Outlines for book on Consumers Union background, approximately 1978 (Box 10)
    - Papers, 1952-1972 (Box 11)
      Scope and Contents
      Includes: Status, Functioning and Prospects of Consumers Union (Robert Brady); Consumer Financed Testing and Rating Agencies (Eugene Beem); The Consumer Reports Subscriber, Portrait of an Intense Consumer (Jack Engledow)
    - Preliminary inventories for files in CSCM, 1978 (Box 11)
    - Proposals for funding, 1975-1978 (Box 11)
    - Sarah Lawrence College proposal for preservation of records of women in the consumer movement, 1976-1978 (Box 11)
    - Staff, 1972-1981 (Box 11)
  - Sybil Shainwald Files, 1971-1984; 2
    - Colston Warne oral history project, 1979-1980 (Box 11)
    - Notes, 1971-1972 (Box 11)
    - Orientation booklet, 1978 (Box 11)
    - Personal, 1972-1979 (Box 11)
    - Testimony, National Women's Health Network, 1984 (Box 11)
  - History Project: Consumers Union the First 20 Years, 1938-1980; 3
    - Background materials, 1938-1980 (Box 12)
    - Chapter drafts--Chapters I-VI, 1972-1974; 7 folders (Box 12)
    - Chapter drafts--Chapters VI-VIII, 1972-1974; 8 folders (Box 13)
    - Chapter drafts--Chapters Viii-XXX, 1972-1974; 11 folders (Box 14)
    - Colston Warne critique and notes, 1974; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Consultants, staff notes, 1939-1954 (Box 15)
    - Outline, 1970-1975 (Box 15)
    - Draft binder (Alan Goodman), 1972-1974; 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Source materials alphabetical files--35th Anniversary to Board of Directors, 1938-1974; 11 folders (Box 15)
    - Source materials alphabetical files--Boycott to Publications, 1938-1974; 38 folders (Box 16)
    - Source materials alphabetical files--Subscription Rates to World's Fair, 1938-1974; 14 folders (Box 17)
- Consumer Policy Institute Records, 1978-1991; 4
  Includes records pertaining to its precursor, the Institute for Consumer Policy Research.
  - A Consumers Guide to Biotechnology proposal, 1988 (Box 18)
  - Below the Line (anti-poverty program), 1987-1988 (Box 18)
  - Budget, 1978-1983 (Box 18)
  - Cleveland-Area Citizens Group proposal, 1980s (Box 18)
  - Conference on Lead Hazards, 1981 (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1988; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Correspondence--Requesting support for proposals, replies, 1978-1979 (Box 18)
  - Ending Poverty, 1986-1988; 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Energy conservation study, 1981-1982 (Box 19)
  - Fact sheets, 1979-1980 (Box 19)
    Including for Institute for Consumer Policy Research
  - Financial, 1981-1984 (Box 19)
  - Financial, 1979-1984; 2 folders (Box 21)
  - Financial, 1983-1984 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Food safety conference, 1980-1984 (Box 19)
  - Health Summit, 1987; 2 folders (Box 19)
  - Hospice project proposals, 1980-1982 (Box 19)
  - Justice for All, 1987 (Box 19)
  - Listing of organizations similar to the Institute, approximately 1979 (Box 19)
  - Low income consumer problems grant proposal, 1979-1980 (Box 19)
  - National Science Foundation grants, 1982-1983 (Box 19)
  - Notifications of grant awards, 1979 (Box 20)
  - Proposals and other documents to establish the Institute for Consumer Policy Research, 1979-1981 (Box 20)
  - Regulatory Information Network Project information packets, 1983 (Box 20)
  - Report--Biotechnology and Milk (Michael Hansen), 1990 (Box 20)
  - Report--Caring at Home for Older Patients with Late-Stage Cancer (Margaret Gold), 1985 (Box 20)
  - Report--Low-Income Consumers (Andrew Eiler), 1979 (Box 20)
  - Report--Older Americans' Guide to Housing and Living Arrangements (Margaret Gold), 1984 (Box 20)
  - Report--Toxic Chemical Accident Risks in New York City (Barbara Warren, Eileen Nic), 1991 (Box 20)
  - Staffing, 1980-1988 (Box 20)
  - Task Force on Corporate Penalties proposal, 1979-1980 (Box 20)
  - Toxic substances, 1986-1987 (Box 20)
  - Work schedule, 1988 (Oversize-folder 1)